## ANKITESH S. RAO

GitHub: https://github.com/AnkiteshR

LinkedIn: https://www.linkedin.com/in/ankiteshsinghrao

Portfolio: https://ankiteshr.github.io Phone No: +1 716 (563)-8128

Email: ankitesh@buffalo.edu

#### **SUMMARY**

Software developer with an experience of 3 years in the field of information technology with a comprehensive background in SQL querying and optimization, database management, ETL, data analysis, visualization, business intelligence, statistical analysis and machine learning. Currently seeking internship/full-time opportunities in data science/data analytics/business intelligence from June 2019.

## **EDUCATION**

## MS in Management Information Systems, University at Buffalo, June 2019 (Expected), 3.83/4.0

 Coursework: Database Management Systems, Distributed Computing and Big Data Technologies, Data Visualization using Tableau, Predictive Analytics, Web Analytics for E-Commerce, Systems Analysis and Design, Management of IT Projects

## Bachelor of Technology in Information Technology, Jaypee Institute of Information Technology (India), May 2015

Coursework: Machine Learning and Big Data Analytics, Database Systems, Data Mining, Information Systems

#### **TECHNICAL SKILLS & CERTIFICATIONS**

- Programming Languages & Databases: Python, SQL, SQL Server, Oracle 11g
- Libraries and Frameworks: NumPy, Pandas, Matlplotlib, Scikit-learn, Seaborn, Keras, OpenCV, TensorFlow
- Statistics: Hypothesis Testing, Exploratory Data Analysis, ANOVA, Descriptive Statistics, Probability Distribution, Sampling Distribution, Regression
- Machine Learning: Pattern Recognition and Predictive Modeling using Classification, Regression, Clustering, Linear Regression, Logistic Regression,
  Decision Trees, Random Forest, Association Rule Mining, Naive Bayes, Neural Network, K-Nearest Neighbors, Recommendation Systems, Support
  Vector Machines, Gradient Descent
- Hadoop Ecosystem: HDFS, MapReduce
- Others: SAS, Google Analytics, Microsoft Power BI, Tableau, MS Excel (Filters/Slicers, VLOOKUP, VBA, Macros etc.), IBM Watson, MS Office
- Certifications: Tableau Desktop Specialist, Querying Microsoft SQL Server 2012/2014 (70-461), Data Warehousing for Business Intelligence, a 5 course specialization, University of Colorado, Coursera, Machine Learning A-Z ™-Hands on Python in Data Science, Udemy

#### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

#### Data Scientist, Delaware North, <u>www.delawarenorth.com</u> at University at Buffalo

Jan 2019 - Present

52 Callodine Ave, Upper

Buffalo, NY 14226

- Developing a facial recognition and transaction processing system for point of sale (POS) kiosks.
- Utilizing Deep Learning, Python, OpenCV, Dlib, TensorFlow and Keras.

## Senior Member Technical, CDK Global www.cdkglobal.com

Mar 2018 - Jul 2018

- Analyzed and optimized existing SQL queries, improving effectiveness by 20%.
- Wrote functions and stored procedures, and updated existing ETL to reduce overall running time of a report from 2 hours to 3 minutes.

## Software Engineer 2, MAQ Software www.maqsoftware.com

Aug 2015 - Jan 2018

- Centralized data pull for more than 15 upstream sources by creating an automated data refresh application through SSIS.
- Processed data collected at data staging layer by writing stored procedure and storing data as facts and dimensions in SQL Data Warehouse.
- Created OLAP Multidimensional Cube (SSAS) to assist business clients in Sales Trend Analysis through Metrics such as MoM, YoY etc.
- Interacted with clients to gather business requirements, modeled them into user stories and negotiated sprint plan for structured delivery process.
- Responsible for researching, replicating, performing root cause analysis and providing solution to the data issues reported by customer.

## **ACADEMIC PROJECTS**

# Logistic Regression Model for Autistic Spectrum Disorder (ASD) Prediction

Jan 2018

- Classified autistic patients based on the screening results and obtained metrics depicting the prevalence of ASD across gender, race and country.
- Built logistic regression model and obtained the ROC Curve and F1 Score. F1 Score after 10-Fold Cross Validation 99.73% (+/- 0.02%).

Utilized: Machine Learning, Python, Numpy, Pandas, Seaborn, Matplotlib, Sklearn, Jupyter Notebook

## Air Quality Prediction based on Relative Humidity

Dec 2018

- Predicted the relative humidity at a given point in time based on the all other attributes affecting the change in RH.
- Split the data into test and train sets and applied linear regression, decision tree, random forest and support vector machine for designing the model for predicting RH.
- Predicted the RMSE (Root Mean Square Error) for the various algorithms and concluded that the random forest algorithm is the best choice.

Utilized: Machine Learning, Python, Numpy, Pandas, Seaborn, Matplotlib, Jupyter Notebook

### **Exploratory Data Analysis and Reporting**

Fall 2018

- Used MS Excel and Tableau Prep to create an employment dataset from the United States Department of Labour, Bureau of Labour Statistics.
- Exported the dataset created to Tableau to create a dashboard (Civilian Labour Force Reporting) to understand the overall employment scenario.
- Performed region, gender, age and race wise analysis, created time series visualizations and did forecasting using Tableau to understand the dynamics of people contributing to the growth.

Utilized: Tableau, Tableau Prep, MS Excel